Maine Acadian Cultural Survey Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic materials, The original materials are stored at Ft. Meade.
  - Color slides, 2380 color slides
    - Geraldine Chasse and Ernie Chasse home, Saint David Village, Madawaska, Maine; Fort Kent Blockhouse, Fort Kent, Maine; Maison Daigle-St. Jean, Clair, New Brunswick, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C013; David A. Whitman; 20 35 mm color slides
      These images document the house of Geraldine and Ernie Chasse in St. David Village, town of Madawaska, ME; 1-3, Exterior of Chasse house; see MAP DW-C012 for more information about the house; 4, Fieldworker Howard Marshall takes a photo of Gerry and Ernie in front of their house; 5, View of St. David Catholic Church from Chasse house; 6, The Chasses' garden; These images document the Fort Kent Blockhouse; 7-8, Fort Kent Blockhouse, 1839 log blockhouse at the confluence of the Fish and St. John River, built by a Maine civil posse as a result of the Maine-New Burnswick boundary dispute; These images document the Maison Daigle-St-Jean in Clair, New Brunswick; 9-19, Exterior of the Maison Daigle-St-Jean, a restored midnineteenth century house; 20, Interior of the Maison Daigle-St-Jean; this type of ceiling was commonly used in Acadian houses. The blue woodwork above the molding appears to have been carved to resemble a rope.
    - Maison Daigle-St-Jean, Clair, New Brunswick, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C014; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Maison Daigle-St-Jean, a restored mid-nineteenth century house in Clair, New Brunswick; 1-5, Interior of the house; the fine carpentry and decorative woodwork attest to the skills of Acadian builders; These images document the Fred Albert house, a mid-nineteenth Acadian house which has been moved from its original location to a site on property owned by the Madawaska Historical Society in St. David Village, ME; 6-7, Loom; 8-15, Furniture and artifacts in the house, including a typical Acadian cupboard and chairs, a churn, and a cast-iron stove; 16-17, Fieldworker Howard Marshall examines a ship's knee in the attic; 18-20, Ship's knee in the attic. Ship's knees, a device used primarily in boat building, are a single piece of wood carved from the part of the tree where the root naturally curves upward into the trunk. Found in a variety of buildings in the study area, they were apparently used in construction until near the end of the nineteenth century (and possibly into the twentieth).
    - Fred Albert house, Saint David, Maine; Ship's knee attic, Edmunston, New Brunswick, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C015; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Fred Albert house, a restored mid-nineteenth century house in St. David, ME; 1, Top half of ship's knee in the attic, showing the heads of the drift pins used to fasten the knee to the top plate of the house. See MAP-DW-C014 for more slides and information; 2-3, Door from the house currently stored in the attic; the chamfered panels are a typical feature of Acadian woodworking; 4-5, Corner joinery and rafters in the attic. Most of the joinery is done with mortises and tenons and secured with wooden pegs. The large timbers forming the frame of the house are hand-hewn; 6-10, Door frame on the main floor; fine woodworking is a hallmark of Acadian construction; 11, Decorative painting on a wall; 12-14, First floor ceiling; this type of ceiling construction was often used by Acadian builders; These images are of scenes in Edmunston, New Brunswick; 15-16, Small market on the outskirts of the city; 17-18, Centre universitaire St-Louis-Maillet, a branch campus of the University of Moncton. The water in the foreground is the Madawaska River; 19-20, Carpet store in Edmunston; the sign, like many in this part of Canada, is in English and French.
    - A. M. Sormany Cites des Jeunes, Edmunston, New Brunswick; Centennial celebration of Sisters of the Immaculate Heart of Mary (Good Shepherd Sisters), Van Buren, Maine; Scenes from Highway 1, Madawaska, Maine, June 19, 1991 - June 21, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C016; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the A. M. Sormany Cites des Jeunes, the secondary school in Edmunston for Francophones; 1-6, Exterior of the school building; These images document a multi-choir concert held at St. Bruno Catholic Church in Van Buren, ME, to honor the centennial of the arrival of the Sisters of the Immaculate Heart of Mary (Good Shepherd Sisters); 7-8, A choir from St-Leonard, New Brunswick performs; 9-10, The choir from St. Bruno Catholic Church; 11-12, Hand painted candle made especially for the Centennial Celebration; 13-14, Altar with candle in front; 15-16, Altar drape made especially for the Centennial Celebration; 17-18, Interior of the church, looking from the front toward the rear, with Centennial banner hanging from balcony; These images were taken on U.S. Highway 1 near the western edge of Madawaska, ME; 19-20, Banner for the Festival Acadien, an annual multi-day event held in Madawaska.
    - Fred Albert House, Saint David, Maine, June 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C017; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      Except for #1-2, these images document the Fred Albert house, located on the property of the Madawaska Historical Society in St. David, ME; 1-2, Welcoming signs at the western edge of Madawaska on U.S. Highway 1; the larger sign in the foreground is permanent, while the smaller sign for the Acadian Festival is temporary; 3-7, Various views of the exterior of the house; the size, shape, and proportion of this house (excluding the porch, a later addition) are representative of a particular style of mid-nineteenth century houses in the study area, many of which are still in use. Typically, these houses have been enlarged and often moved from their original location; this particular house has been moved more than once; 8-15, Details of the porch and railings; it is probable that the porch was a later addition, most likely added when the house was moved and enlarged. Field coordinator Ray Brassieur suggests that the posts and railings are stylistically quite nautical; 16-17, Rear door, with chamfered panels typical of Acadian woodwork; 18, Wildflowers on the grounds outside the house; 19-20, Artifacts in the house; the cupboard and chairs are typical Acadian furniture.
    - Fred Albert house, Saint David, Maine; Maison Daigle-St-Jean, Clair, New Brunswick, June 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C018; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Fred Albert house, a typical mid-nineteenth century Acadian house, which has been moved to its present site on property owned by the Madawaska Historical Society in St. David, ME; 1-3, Fieldworker Howard Marshall examines and photographs a cupboard in the Albert house; this cupboard, with chamfered panels on the inside of the doors, is a typical Acadian piece; 4, Close-up of cupboard door; 5, Acadian chairs; 6-7, Wash stand and chair; 8, Spinning wheel; 9-10, Back door; again, note the chamfered panels. # 10, Marshall photographs the door; 11-12, Loom and other artifacts, including Acadian textiles; 13-14, Another loom; 15, Front stairs; steeply inclined stairs are typical in houses of this vintage; 16-17, Back stairs; These images document the Maison Daigle-St-Jean, a mid-nineteenth century Acadian house in Clair, New Brunswick, which has been moved and restored by the Clair Historical Society; 18-20, Stove and opening in wall for air circulation.
    - Maison Daigle-St-Jean, Clair, New Brunswick; Acadian Festival talent show, Madawaska, Maine, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C019; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Maison Daigle-St-John, a restored nineteenth century house in Clair, New Brunswick; 1-6, Various interior scenes on the main floor of the house; 7-11, Collection of artifacts in the attic; also visible in slides 8-11 is a ship's knee, a nautical construction device which has been found in several buildings in the study area; 12, Hand-carved handle; 13-14, Stairs leading from the attic to a small loft; this loft was probably added during a period when the house was being enlarged to accommodate the family's growth; 15-16, Interior roof construction. It is difficult to tell if these rafters are lapped or joined with mortise and tenon; both methods were common in the houses built at this time; These images document the talent show held as a part of the annual Acadian Festival in Madawaska, ME; 17-19, Opening ceremony, including a prayer and recitation of the statement "Je suis fier d'etre Acadien" (I am proud to be Acadian). The leaders of the ceremony are dressed in clothing purportedly representative of traditional Acadian garb. Note the four flags on the left— America, Canada, New Brunswick, and Acadia— as well as the large Acadian flag which serves as a backdrop; 20, Talent show MC Beurmond Banville.
    - Acadian Festival Talent Show, Madawaska, Maine, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C020; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the talent show held as part of the annual Acadian Festival in Madawaska, ME; 1-6, Annick Gagnon, the featured performer at the talent show. Annick is a young (age thirteen at the time of this performance) Canadian woman who is developing a career as a professional singer, and enjoys widespread popularity in the region; she sings in both French and English; 7-10, Fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and Lisa Ornstein examine souvenirs and talk with a member of the Keystone Kops, a local organization of volunteer men who appear at many functions in the study area, where they provide "security" and engage in assorted hijinks; 11, Quilt (which really appeared to be a woven coverlet) raffled during Acadian Festival; 12, Souvenir sweatshirts with a graphic depicting certain features of the town of Madawaska; these are sold throughout the year at the Madawaska Chamber of Commerce, not only at the Acadian Festival; 14, Annick Gagnon continues her performance after a costume change; 15, One of the Acadian Festival volunteer organizers is interviewed by local media; 16, Annick Gagnon is joined onstage by her sisters and someone in a Mickey Mouse costume while performing "It's a Small, Small World"; 17, Gert Daigle, a local woman, performs "God Bless the Foreign Land," a song she had written to honor American soldiers participating in the war against Iraq (Operation Desert Storm); 18, Daigle is joined by another local woman (name unknown) in a performance of a song with a Christian message; 19, MC Beurmond Banville; 20, A baton twirler; all the performers except Annick Gagnon were local amateurs and performed without pay.
    - Acadian Festival talent show, Madawaska, Maine; Acadian Mass, Saint David, Maine, June 26, 1991 - June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C021; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the talent show held as part of the annual Acadian Festival in Madawaska, ME; 1, A Canadian woman, name unknown, performs a traditional dance; 2, A former local beauty pageant queen who now lives out of state, who returned to perform a song at the talent show; 3, Local fiddler Lionel Doucette, who performed three tunes; 4, George Sullivan, an employee of Fraser Paper in Madawaska, performs a humorous skit which included impressions of Louis Armstrong; 5, Jennifer Michaud, the current Miss Greater Madawaska, performs a song; These images document the Acadian Mass, held annually at St. David Catholic Church in St. David, ME, during the Acadian Festival week; 6-7, Family members line up behind their respective banners for the procession at the start of the mass; 8, The procession begins; 9, Part of the congregation; 10-17, The procession continues; each family which has previously held a reunion during the Acadian festival has a banner which is carried in and laid in front of the altar; 18, The last members of the initial procession; the woman's costume is intended to replicate traditional Acadia garb; 19, The priests at the altar begin the mass; 20, Part of the congregation.
    - Acadian Mass, Saint David, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C022; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Acadian Mass, held annually at St. David Catholic Church in St. David, ME, during the Acadian Festival week; 1, Part of the congregation; 2-3, A priest performs a part of the Mass; 4-7, Various readings were done by lay people during the Mass. the woman in #6-7 is wearing clothes meant to replicate traditional Acadian garb; 9-12, Various parts of the Mass; 13-14, People receiving communion; 15-18, The recessional; as in the processional, families walk behind their respective banners; 19-20, A house in Madawaska, ME; the use of vivid greens and blues to paint houses is quite prevalent in the study area.
    - Houses and miscellaneous scenes, Madawaska, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C023; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings, mostly houses, and other scenes in Madawaska, ME. Specific structures were chosen to photograph based on color— in particular, the use of vivid greens and blues, and the use of a slightly varying shade of red-brown which is often called oxblood (or sang de boeuf in French); 1-6, Various houses; 7-8, Fire hydrant; the use of the bright green echoes a color often used in painting buildings; 9-17, Various houses; 18, A rural scene in Madawaska; the long, narrow field traversing the hill reminds one of the French long lot style of land grants; 19, Some sort of municipal building along a stream which is painted with the same sort of green often seen on houses; 20, House in Madawaska; the butterflies on the exterior wall are a commonly used decorative device in the study area.
    - Variety of houses in Madawaska, Maine; Acadian Mass, Saint David Catholic Church, Madawaska, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C024; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document several different houses in Madawaska, ME; these houses were chosen to photograph to typify certain decorative aspects common in the study area; 1-3, House with large decorative butterflies; 4-6, Several different houses, each using a red-brown shade of paint either on walls or trim; 7-9, Different houses painted in vivid green/blue shades; These images document the Acadian Mass held annually at St. David Catholic Church in Madawaska, ME, during the Acadian Festival week; 10-20, After the mass, the congregation was led by the past and present reunion families in a procession from the church to the cross commemorating the Acadian landing site. In #16, fieldworker Lisa Ornstein photographs the procession.
    - Acadian Mass held during the Acadien Festival week, Saint David, Maine; Various buildings, Madawaska, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C025; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Acadian Mass held annually at St. David Catholic Church during the Acadian Festival week; 1-15, The congregation is led by reunion families with their banners in a procession from the church to the cross commemorating the Acadian landing site. #2-3, Geraldine Chasse is seen in a costume meant to replicate traditional Acadian garb. #4, small markers and trees represent each of the families having had a reunion in conjunction with the Acadian Festival; each year, a particular family has a large reunion which is a kind of centerpiece for the Festival; 16-17, John's Hardware on Main St. in Madawaska; the bright blue/green color is found on many buildings, primarily houses, in the study area; 18-20, Headquarters of the Acadian Festival on Main St., Madawaska.
    - Various buildings, Madawaska, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C026; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings in Madawaska, ME. Particular buildings were chosen to photograph as evidence of typical or special decorative or architectural features; 1-2, Video store in on Main St.; note the use of the Acadian flag as a decoration; 3, Jewelry store on Main St.; Acadian flag used as decoration, and the SALE banner in the window uses the Acadian colors, although not in the same pattern as the flag; 4-7, Various houses, including a mobile home, using bright blue or green paint; 8, Oscar and Delphine Daigle on the porch of their house; 9-20, A variety of houses, all of which have been painted using vivid blue/green shades.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Frenchville, Maine, and St. Agatha, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C027; David A. Whitman; 17 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of scenes and buildings in Frenchville and St. Agatha, ME; particular buildings were chosen to photograph as evidence of typical or special decorative or architectural features; 1, House with lawn ornaments on U.S. Highway 1 in Frenchville; 2, Wildflowers, a great many of which grow in the study area; the white flowers are daisies; 3-8, Buildings painted with a red-brown, sometimes called oxblood, shade which is widely used. The building in #7-8 has a facade which, while often associated with commercial buildings, is found on many non-commercial buildings in the study area; 9-11, Several houses painted with bright blue/green shades, a common decorative theme; 13-15, Wagon of the Keystone Kops parked in a driveway in St. Agatha; 15-17, House in St. Agatha which combines the use of green and oxblood colors. Other decorative features often found in the study area are lawn ornaments, particularly the chrome ball, and the eagle; 18-20, Do not exist.
    - Potato farm in New Canada, Maine; Various scenes in Madawaska, Maine, June 28, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C028; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the potato farm of Orenie Bossie and Sons in New Canada, ME; 1, Barn with potato barrels stacked outside; 2, Field of young oats. Most farmers plant some sort of grain, often oats, along with potatoes; sometimes these are used as rotation crops; 3, Produce storage barn called a potato house; often, these are partially buried as an insulating technique; 4-5, Small garden on the farm; note that the plants are still covered for protection against possible frost, although it is late June; 6, Another view of the fields; 7, Notice on door to potato house, warning against contamination of seed potatoes; 8, Field of young potato plants, probably planted about three weeks ago; 9, Handmade wooden potato barrels, seldom used in modern harvesting; 10, Barn and shed. Note the custom painted sign with MPG (Maine Potato Growers) logo; these are found on many farms in the study area; The following images are of a variety of scenes in Madawaska, ME; 11-12, Sign at gas station on Main St. announcing aspects of Acadian Festival; 13, Sirois Sharpening Service truck; 14-16, Barn on a farm on Beaulieu Rd.; the connected in-line barns are an unusual type. It is unknown if the barns are currently in use; 17, Potato field (foreground) and view of the St. John River Valley; 18-20, Former house now used as storage on a farm; the smaller section is probably an addition to the original house.
    - Various houses and scenes, Madawaska, Maine, June 27, 1991 - June 28, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C029; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes in Madawaska, ME; 1-3, House with trim painted in widely-used red-brown color. #3, note the pelican on the steps; pelicans are not native fauna, but pelican statues are frequently used as decorative items; 4, Truck with bright blue/green paint, echoing shades often used to paint houses; 5, Houses painted with bright blue/green colors; 6, House using a gray and red-brown color combination; this combination is often used in the study area; 7, Store in Lavertu Settlement; note the pavilion roofline with a break, often associated with French architecture in the United States, but not commonly used in the study area; 8-10, Houses with broken rooflines and incised porches in Lavertu Settlement; 13, House with gray and red color combination; 14-16, Barn in Madawaska; the gambrel (colm-casse) roof is a common feature in the study area, but the addition which wraps around nearly three-quarters of the barn is not; 17-18, Houses using bright blue/green colors; 19, Old bus parked behind a house; the gray and red color scheme echoes that use in many houses; 20, Handmade wooden potato barrels.
    - Abandoned farmhouse, Madawaska, Maine; Musical spoons in collection of Nicolo Gagne, Clair, New Brunswick; Acadian Festival parade, Madawaska, Maine, June 28, 1991 - June 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C030; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      A couple of miscellaneous images; 1, Abandoned house converted to storage on a farm on Beaulieu Rd. in Madawaska; the smaller section was probably an addition; 2, A collection of musical spoons belonging to Clair, New Brunswick resident Nicolo Gagne; the wooden spoons were purchased from other makers in Quebec and New Brunswick, while the metal spoons were made by M. Gagne; These images document the annual Acadian Festival parade; 3-20, Scenes from the annual Acadian Festival parade in Madawaska, which proceeds down Main St. and ends at the Madawaska High School. The parade is very well attended, and many organizations and businesses in Madawaska and throughout the study area are represented.
    - Acadian Festival Parade, Madawaska, Maine, June 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C031; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the annual parade held as part of the Acadian Festival. The parade route went through the center of downtown on Main St., which is where these photographs were taken, and finished at the Madawaska High School; 1-6, A color guard performs in front of the judges, who were stationed on the balcony of the Acadian Festival headquarters (the gray building in #3-4). The solitary soldier in camouflage in #2 represented the troops serving in Operation Desert Storm; 7-14, A youth group known as the Firing Squad; 15, Unknown group marches with a variety of flags, including American and Acadian flags and provincial flags of Canada; 16, Aroostook County Democrats; 17-20, Group with POW/MIA display.
    - Acadian Festival Parade, Madawaska, Maine, June 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C032; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the annual parade held as part of the Acadian Festival. See MAP-DW-C031 for more information; 1-2, Group with POW/MIA display; 3-4, Unknown group (Knights of Columbus?) marching with flags, including Acadian, American, and provincial flags of Canada; 5, Knights of Columbus car; 6-7, Les Chevaliers de Colomb (Canadian equivalent of Knights of Columbus) de St-Jacques; 8, A beauty pageant winner; 9, Optimist International; 10, Jennifer Michaud, 1991 Miss Greater Madawaska; 11, Big Bird, a character form the television show Sesame Street; 12-13, Various Disney characters; 14, Popular children's television and movie characters the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles; 15-17, Stunt bicyclists; 18, Winners of Optimist Mini-Kar races; 19, Antique car with local business advertisement; 20, The Marching Owls, Madawaska High School band.
    - Acadian Festival Parade, Madawaska, Maine, June 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C033; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides